It would be nice to be objective in life,
إنه لشيءٌ جميل أن تكون موضوعيًا في الحياة
in many ways.
بعدّة طرق.
The problem is that we have these color-tinted glasses
المشكله أن لدينا تلك النظارات الملونة
as we look at all kinds of situations.
عندما ننظر في كل أنواع المواقف.
For example, think about something as simple as beer.
كمثال: فكر بشيء بسيط كالجعة.
If I gave you a few beers to taste
إذا أعطيتك بعض زجاجات الجعة لتتذوقها
and I asked you to rate them on intensity and bitterness,
وطلبت منك تقييمها تبعًا للحدّة والمرارة،
different beers would occupy different space.
ستشغل أنواع جعة مختلفة مكانة مختلفة لديك.
But what if we tried to be objective about it?
لكن ماذا لوحاولنا أن نكون موضوعيين بشأنها؟
In the case of beer, it would be very simple.
بحالة الجعة، سيكون الوضع بسيطًا جدًا.
What if we did a blind taste?
ماذا لو قمنا بتذوق عشوائي؟
Well, if we did the same thing, you tasted the same beer,
حسناً، إنْ فعلنا نفس الشيء، قمتَ بتذوق نفس الجعة،
now in the blind taste, things would look slightly different.
لكن الآن بتذوق عشوائي، فسيبدو الوضع مختلفًا قليلًا.
Most of the beers will go into one place.
ستأخذ معظم أنواع الجعة مكانة واحدة.
You will basically not be able to distinguish them,
ببساطة لن تكون قادرًا على تمييزها.
and the exception, of course, will be Guinness.
و الاستثناء طبعا سيكون (جعة غينيس)
Similarly, we can think about physiology.
وبطريقة مماثلة، يمكننا التفكير بعلم وظائف الأعضاء.
What happens when people expect something from their physiology?
ماذا يحدث عندما يتوقع الناس شيئًا من أجسادهم
For example, we sold people pain medications.
مثال: بعنا الناس أدوية مسكنة للألم.
Some people, we told them the medications were expensive.
قلنا لبعضهم أنها أدوية غالية الثمن.
Some people, we told them it was cheap.
وقلنا للبعض الآخر أنها أدوية رخيصة.
And the expensive pain medication worked better.
والأدوية غالية الثمن عملت بشكل أفضل.
It relieved more pain from people,
أزالت الألم من الناس بدرجة أكبر.
because expectations do change our physiology.
لأن التوقعات تحدث تغييرًا بوظائف أجسادنا
And of course, we all know that in sports,
وبالطبع، كلنا نعلم أنه في الرياضة،
if you are a fan of a particular team,
إذا كنت مشجعًا لفريق معين،
you can't help but see the game
لايمكنك إلا أن تنظر للعبة
develop from the perspective of your team.
من منظور فريقك.
So all of those are cases in which our preconceived notions
فبكل هذه الحالات لدينا أفكار سابقة
and our expectations color our world.
وتوقعاتنا تلوّن عالمنا.
But what happened in more important questions?
لكن ماذا يحدث مع الأسئلة الأكثر أهمية؟
What happened with questions that had to do with social justice?
ماذا يحدث مع الأسئلة المتعلقة بالعدالة الاجتماعية؟
So we wanted to think about what is the blind tasting version
لذا فكرنا ما هي النسخة المناسبة من اختبار التذوق العشوائي
for thinking about inequality?
عند التفكير بعدم المساواة؟
So we started looking at inequality,
فبدأنا النظر في عدم المساواة،
and we did some large-scale surveys
وأجرينا دراسات استقصائية واسعة النطاق
around the U.S. and other countries.
في الولايات المتحدة وبعض البلدان الأخرى.
So we asked two questions:
و سألنا سؤالين:
Do people know what kind of level of inequality we have?
هل يعلم الناس مستوى عدم المساواة لدينا؟
And then, what level of inequality do we want to have?
ومن ثم، ما هو مستوى عدم المساواة الذي نريده في مجتمعنا؟
So let's think about the first question.
فلنفكر في السؤال الأول.
Imagine I took all the people in the U.S.
تخيل أني أخذت كل الناس في الولايات المتحدة
and I sorted them from the poorest on the right
وفرزتهم من الأفقر على اليمين
to the richest on the left,
إلى الأغنى على اليسار،
and then I divided them into five buckets:
ومن ثم قسمتهم لخمسة مجموعات
the poorest 20 percent, the next 20 percent,
الأفقر 20%، والتالي 20%،
the next, the next, and the richest 20 percent.
والتالي، والتالي، والأغنى 20% .
And then I asked you to tell me how much wealth do you think
وسألتك كم تظن هي كمية الثروة
is concentrated in each of those buckets.
المركّزة في كل مجموعة.
So to make it simpler, imagine I ask you to tell me,
ولأجعلها أبسط تخيل أني سألتك:
how much wealth do you think is concentrated
كم تظن هي كمية الثروة المركّزة
in the bottom two buckets,
في المجموعتين الأخيرتين؟
the bottom 40 percent?
في أدنى 40%
Take a second. Think about it and have a number.
خذ ثانية. فكر فيها وخمن رقم
Usually we don't think.
عادةً لا نفكر.
Think for a second, have a real number in your mind.
فكّر لثانية، وضع رقمًا في ذهنك
You have it?
هل فعلت؟
Okay, here's what lots of Americans tell us.
حسنًا، هذا ما أجابنا به العديد من الأمريكيين.
They think that the bottom 20 percent
هم يظنون أن ال 20% الدّنيا
has about 2.9 percent of the wealth,
تأخذ 2.9% من الثروة،
the next group has 6.4,
والمجموعة التالية تأخذ 6.4،
so together it's slightly more than nine.
إذا مع بعضهم يشكِّلون تقريبًا أكثر من 9
The next group, they say, has 12 percent,
ويقولون أن المجموعة التالية تأخذ 12%
20 percent,
ثم 20% ،
and the richest 20 percent, people think has 58 percent of the wealth.
وأغنى 20 %، يظن الناس أنها تأخذ 58 % من الثروة.
You can see how this relates to what you thought.
يمكنك الآن أن ترى مدى التطابق مع ما كنت تظنه.
Now, what's reality?
والأن ما هو الواقع؟
Reality is slightly different.
الواقع مختلف قليلًا.
The bottom 20 percent has 0.1 percent of the wealth.
ال20% الدُّنيا تأخذ 0.1 % من الثروة.
The next 20 percent has 0.2 percent of the wealth.
ال20% التالية تأخذ 0.2 % من الثروة .
Together, it's 0.3.
مع بعضهم 0.3
11.3,
ثم 11.3
and the richest group has 84-85 percent of the wealth.
والمجموعة الأغنى تأخذ 84-85 % من الثروة.
So what we actually have and what we think we have
فما لدينا فعلًا وما نظن أنه لدينا
are very different.
مختلفان كثيرًا.
What about what we want?
ماذا عن ما نريد؟
How do we even figure this out?
كيف لنا حتى أن نعرف؟
So to look at this,
وبالتالي للنظر في ذلك،
to look at what we really want,
للنظر بماذا نريد حقًّا،
we thought about the philosopher John Rawls.
فكّرنا بالفيلسوف جون رولز.
If you remember John Rawls,
إذا كنتم تذكرون جون رولز
he had this notion of what's a just society.
كان لديه ذلك المبدأ عن ماهية المجتمع العادل
He said a just society
لقد قال: المجتمع العادل
is a society that if you knew everything about it,
هو المجتمع الذي إذا عرفت عنه كل شيء
you would be willing to enter it in a random place.
ستكون مستعدًا للدخول فيه بمكانة عشوائية.
And it's a beautiful definition,
وهو تعريفٌ جميل،
because if you're wealthy, you might want the wealthy
لأنه إذا كنت غنيًا لربما أردت
to have more money, the poor to have less.
أن يأخذ الأغنياء أكثر والفقراء أقل.
If you're poor, you might want more equality.
وإذا كنت فقيرًا لربما أردت مساواة أكثر
But if you're going to go into that society
ولكن إذا كنت ستدخل بذلك المجتمع
in every possible situation, and you don't know,
بأيَّ مكانة محتملة ولا تعرفها،
you have to consider all the aspects.
يجب عليك الأخذ بعين الأعتبار كل الاحتمالات
It's a little bit like blind tasting in which you don't know
وهذا يشبه قليلًا التذوق العشوائي لكونك لا تعرف
what the outcome will be when you make a decision,
ما ستكون النتيجة عندما تأخذ قرارًا،
and Rawls called this the "veil of ignorance."
وهذا ما دعاه رولز "حجاب الجهل".
So, we took another group, a large group of Americans,
لذلك أخذنا مجموعة كبيرة أخرى من الأمريكيين
and we asked them the question in the veil of ignorance.
وسألناهم السؤال بحجاب الجهل.
What are the characteristics of a country that would make you want to join it,
ماهي صفات الدولة التي ستجعلك راغبًا بالانضمام إليها،
knowing that you could end randomly at any place?
مع العلم أنه يمكن أن ينتهي فيك المطاف بأيَّ طبقة.
And here is what we got.
وهذا ما حصلنا عليه
What did people want to give to the first group,
ماذا أراد الناس أن تُعطي المجموعة الأولى،
the bottom 20 percent?
ال 20% الأدنى ؟
They wanted to give them about 10 percent of the wealth.
أرادوا إعطائهم حوالي 10% من الثروة.
The next group, 14 percent of the wealth,
والمجموعة التالية ، 14% من الثروة،
21, 22 and 32.
21 و22 و32
Now, nobody in our sample wanted full equality.
ولا شخص من عيِّنتنا أراد مساواة كاملة.
Nobody thought that socialism is a fantastic idea in our sample.
ولا شخص فكَّر أن الاشتراكية ستكون فكرة عظيمة.
But what does it mean?
لكن ماذا يعني هذا؟
It means that we have this knowledge gap
هذا يعني أن لدينا فجوة معرفية
between what we have and what we think we have,
بين ما لدينا وما نظن أنه لدينا،
but we have at least as big a gap between what we think is right
ولكن لدينا فجوة على الأقل بنفس الحجم بين ما نظنه عادلًا
to what we think we have.
وما نظن أنه لدينا.
Now, we can ask these questions, by the way, not just about wealth.
والآن، يمكننا أن نسأل هذه الأسئلة، على فكرة، ليس فقط عن الثروة.
We can ask it about other things as well.
بل يمكننا أن نسألها عن أشياء أخرى أيضًا.
So for example, we asked people from different parts of the world
فمثلا، سألنا أشخاصًا من مختلف أنحاء العالم
about this question,
عن هذه الأسئلة،
people who are liberals and conservatives,
أشخاص من الليبراليين والمحافظين،
and they gave us basically the same answer.
ولقد أعطونا أساسًا نفس الجواب.
We asked rich and poor, they gave us the same answer,
سألنا الأغنياء والفقراء، وأعطونا نفس الجواب،
men and women,
رجال ونساء،
NPR listeners and Forbes readers.
مستمعي الإذاعة الوطنية العامة وقراء فوربس.
We asked people in England, Australia, the U.S. --
سألنا الناس في إنكلترا وأستراليا والولايات المتحدة...
very similar answers.
أجوبة متشابهة جدًا.
We even asked different departments of a university.
لقد سألنا حتى الأقسام المختلفة في الجامعة.
We went to Harvard and we checked almost every department,
ذهبنا لهارفرد وسألنا تقريبًا كل الأقسام،
and in fact, from Harvard Business School,
وفي الواقع، في مدرسة هارفرد للأعمال،
where a few people wanted the wealthy to have more and the [poor] to have less,
أراد قلة من الأشخاص أن يُعطي الأغنياء أكثر والفقراء أقل .
the similarity was astonishing.
التشابه كان مذهلًا.
I know some of you went to Harvard Business School.
أنا أعلم أن بعضكم درس في مدرسة هارفرد للأعمال.
We asked, what about the ratio of CEO pay to unskilled workers?
سألنا ماذا عن نسبة راتب المدير التنفيذي مقارنة بالعمال قليلي المهارة.
So you can see what people think is the ratio,
لكي نرى كم يظن الناس حجم النسبة،
and then we can ask the question, what do they think should be the ratio?
ولنتمكن بعدها من سؤالهم : كم برأيهم يجب أن تكون النسبة؟
And then we can ask, what is reality?
وبعدها يمكننا أن نسأل : ما هو الواقع؟
The red and the yellow are not that different.
الأحمر والأصفر ليسا مختلفين كثيرًا.
But the fact is, it's because I didn't draw them on the same scale.
ولكن في الواقع، هذا لأنني لم أرسمهما على نفس المقياس.
It's hard to see, there's yellow and blue in there.
إنه لمن الصعب رؤية أية أحمر والأصفر هناك.
So what about other outcomes of wealth?
حسنًا، ماذا عن النتائج الأخرى للثروة؟
Wealth is not just about wealth.
الثروة ليست فقط عن الثروة.
We asked, what about things like health?
سألنا ، ماذا عن الأشياء الأخرى كالصحة؟
What about availability of prescription medication?
ماذا عن توافر الأدوية الموصوفة؟
What about life expectancy?
ماذا عن متوسط العمر المتوقع؟
What about life expectancy of infants?
ماذا عن متوسط العمر المتوقع لدى الرضّع؟
How do we want this to be distributed?
كيف نريد هذا أن يتوزع؟
What about education for young people?
ماذا عن التعليم للشباب؟
And for older people?
وللمسنين؟
And across all of those things, what we learned was that people
ومن خلال كل ذلك تعلمنا أن الناس
don't like inequality of wealth,
لا يعجبهم عدم المساواة بتوزيع الثروة.
but there's other things where inequality, which is an outcome of wealth,
ولكن هناك أشياء أخرى حيث لايوجد مساواة فيها كنتيجة للثروة
is even more aversive to them:
يعد منفرًا أكثر بالنسبة لهم.
for example, inequality in health or education.
مثلًا: عدم المساواة في الصحة أو التعليم.
We also learned that people are particularly open
وتعلمنا أيضًا أن الناس منفتحون على إزالة
to changes in equality when it comes to people
عدم المساواة خاصة عندما يتعلق الأمر
who have less agency --
بالناس قليلي القوة --
basically, young kids and babies,
بشكل أساسي، الأطفال والأولاد الصغار،
because we don't think of them as responsible for their situation.
لأننا لا ننظر لهم كأشخاص مسؤولين عن وضعهم.
So what are some lessons from this?
إذًا ما هي الدروس من هذا؟
We have two gaps:
لدينا فجوتان:
We have a knowledge gap and we have a desirability gap
لدينا فجوة معرفية ولدينا فجوة الرغبة.
And the knowledge gap is something that we think about,
الفجوة المعرفية هي شيء نفكر فيه:
how do we educate people?
كيف نعلّم الناس؟
How do we get people to think differently about inequality
كيف نجعل الناس تفكر بطريقة مختلفة حول مسألة عدم المساواة
and the consequences of inequality in terms of health, education,
ونتائج عدم المساواة من ناحية الصحة والتعليم
jealousy, crime rate, and so on?
والغيرة ومعدل الجرائم... إلى أخره؟
Then we have the desirability gap.
ثم لدينا فجوة الرغبة.
How do we get people to think differently about what we really want?
كيف نجعل الناس تفكر بطريقة مختلفة حول ما نرغب به حقًا؟
You see, the Rawls definition, the Rawls way of looking at the world,
تعريف رولز، وطريقة رولز بالنظر للعالم،
the blind tasting approach,
أسلوب التذوق العشوائي،
takes our selfish motivation out of the picture.
يخرج دوافعنا الأنانية من الصورة.
How do we implement that to a higher degree
كيف نطبق ذلك على درجة أعلى
on a more extensive scale?
وعلى مقياس أوسع؟
And finally, we also have an action gap.
وفي النهاية لدينا فجوة في الأداء.
How do we take these things and actually do something about it?
كيف نأخذ هذه الأفكار ونفعل شيئًا حيالها؟
like young kids and babies that don't have much agency,
كالأطفال والأولاد الصغار الذين لا يملكون الكثير من القوة
because people seem to be more willing to do this.
لأن الناس تبدو مستعدة أكثر لتفعل ذلك.
To summarize, I would say, next time you go to drink beer or wine,
كتلخيص أقول: في المرة القادمة عندما تذهب لشرب الجعة أو النبيذ
first of all, think about, what is it in your experience that is real,
قبل كل شيء، فكر ما هو الحقيقي في تجربتك،
and what is it in your experience that is a placebo effect
وما هو الوهمي فيها
coming from expectations?
الذي يأتي من التوقعات؟
And then think about what it also means for other decisions in your life,
ثم فكر بما يعنيه أيضًا في القرارات الأخرى بحياتك،
and hopefully also for policy questions
وعلى أمل أيضًا في المسائل السياسية
that affect all of us.
التي تؤثر علينا جميعا.
Thanks a lot.
شكرًا جزيلًا.